Let's discuss completing your PMP
application.
So you'll want to create an account at PMI
.org.
And then you'll click on the button for
PMP certification.
Good way to start is getting your resume.
We often forget what projects we worked on
and how long.
So that will help you populate your
application.
I highly recommend that you become a PMI
member.
It is not mandatory, but gives you all
kinds of added benefits.
A big one is you'll be able to sign up for
their sister site, Project Management.com,
and you have access to
all kinds of templates that
you can start using on
your projects for free.
You also have access to all kinds of
webinars, on-demand videos that will help
you get your PDUs, your professional
development units.
All right, so it's worth having.
All right.
The minimum requirements for taking the
PMP exam.
If you have a bachelor's
degree, you need to be able to
show verifiable 36 months of
project management experience.
You might not have the
title of project manager,
but you have taken a
project from beginning to end.
That's the key part,
showing you have experience,
and it must be within
the past eight years.
If you don't have a bachelor's,
then you'll need 60 months verifiable
experience of project management project
lead experience and again within the past
eight years you can't go beyond those
eight years all right last but not least
you need 35 hours of relevant education
which you are getting right now so you
want to go ahead and fill out your
application use your resume to get started
get it populated your application will be
saved for 90 days.
So if you start it, you don't have to
worry about finishing it right away.
All right.
Big, big piece, this first little
sub-bullet here.
Overlapping months only count once.
So you can't work on one project eight
hours a day and say that you're also
working on another project same time eight
hours a day.
PMI only allows eight hours of work per
day.
That's all they recognize, although most
of us never just work eight hours.
That's all you can use.
So if you're working on simultaneous
projects, however many you have,
eight hours a day, if they are
overlapping.
All right, this next sub bullet,
you want to use high level project
descriptions, non-technical, non-industry
jargon.
It needs to be very clear to anybody who
saw your application, how you've taken a
project from beginning to end,
initiating all the way to closing.
Once you submit your application,
you might get audited.
Audits are random, but very common.
So PMI will send you an email saying
you're being audited.
It's basically a paper
trail, but they will give you
all the information exactly
what to do for that audit.
Last but not least, PMI usually will
respond within five business days to let
you know whether your application is
approved or rejected.
Usually the only time it's
rejected is if you've listed
overlapping projects or, you know,
over the eight years experience.
So be careful when you submit your
application.
Lastly, once your application is approved,
you can pay for the exam.
So you will pay for the exam.
So you will pay for the exam on the PMI
website, you will
receive an eligibility ID.
You do not have to schedule the exam right
away.
Most people need quite a bit of time to
study and test.
And I'm talking full-blown simulated exams
to fully prepare.
You need to understand what questions and
answers are going to be, what they're
actually asking with the answers out of
the four and some of the other types of
questions they have now, what those could
be.
Practice, practice, practice, practice
makes perfect.
All right.
Last but not least, when
you are ready to schedule
your exam, you'll go to
the Pearson View website.
You can either have an online proctor
test.
You're at home with your computer and
someone is watching you the entire time,
by the way, or you can go to the testing
center.
you'll be able to put in your zip code
close to where you live or work and
they'll show a testing
facility that's closest to you
in available times we'll
talk about this more later